Register of the Nikolai Nikolaevich Golovin papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Nikolai Nikolaevich Golovin papers
1912-1943
47013
Hoover Institution Archives
18 manuscript boxes (7.5 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, and printed matter relating to Russian military activities during World War I, the Russian Civil War, and the Sino-Japanese War.
Golovin, N. N. (Nikolai Nikolaevich), 1875-1944.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1947.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (18 reels).
Biographical Note
General, Russian Imperial army.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, speeches and writings, and printed matter relating to Russian military activities during World War I, the Russian Civil War, and the Sino-Japanese War.
Russia. Armiia--Officers; Russia.; Sino-Japanese Conflict, 1937-1945.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.; World War, 1914-1918.
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1937-1941 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, arranged chronologically.
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1912-1937 (Boxes 1-12)
  Drafts and printed copies of speeches and writings, arranged alphabetically by title.
  - "Ashmore Modernized" (Box 1)
  - "Contemporary Strategical-Political Situation in China"
  - "Contest for China"
  - "Cossacks Abroad"
  - "Far Eastern Problem," lecture noes
  - "Letters on Russia, 1920" / Materials on the Red Army
  - Published works of General N. Golovin, list / Paris, 1928
  - "Red Army and Navy, 1924-1926"
  - "In Response to General Melgunov's Critical Remarks, Concerning The Russian Counter-Revolution in 1917-1918" (Box 2)
  - "Russian Counter-Revolution, 1917-1918"
    - Appendices, I, II
    - Bibliography
    - Chronology
    - Foreword
    - Maps
    - Chapters I-IX
    - Chapters X-XXVI (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous drafts (Boxes 4-5)
    - Miscellaneous drafts (Boxes 6-9)
    - Miscellaneous drafts (Box 10)
    - Correspondence with Helene von Damm and Elena Varneck regarding preparation of text of publication
  - "Sino-Japanese Conflict," lecture notes, 19?? March 9 (Box 11)
  - "Sino-Japanese Conflict," lecture notes and clippings, 1932 March 15
  - "Sociology of War," Paris, 1938
  - "Strategy in Military Action"
    - "General H. D. Bulow, 1760-1806"
    - "Karl of Austria, 1771-1847"
    - "General H. Jomini, 1779-1869"
    - "General Leval" (Box 12)
    - "General H. Lloyd, 1729-1783"
    - "General Baron N. V. Medem, 1796-1870"
  - "Swords and Plowshares"
- SUBJECT FILE, 1914-1943 (Boxes 12-16)
  Correspondence, reports, lists, and printed matter, arranged alphabetically by title and subject.
  - "Account of Battles Fought in the Vicinity of Tilsit, August 28-31, 1941" (Box 12)
  - "Activity of XVth Army Corps in Oriental Prussia in 1914"
  - Agreement between the Governments of the Don, Kuban', Terek, and Astrakhan', Crimea, 1920
  - Agreement signed by the Governments of the Don, Kuban', and Terek, 1921 January 1 (14)
  - Akaro, Lt. Colonel, "Cavalry Attack by the 2nd Brigade of the XIV Cavalry Division of the Units of the XI German Army Corps, near the Village of Neradovo,", 1915 July 3 (13)
  - Akulin, General I., notes on the action of the 3rd Don Cossack Division in the Battle with the Sukhodols in 1914
  - Arkhangelsky, Colonel P. G., "Participation of the 35th Infantry Division in the Vicinity of Tarnoshin on August 14 or 15, 1914"
  - Associations of Military Science in Emigration
  - Awards, certificates, congratulatory letters, etc. (Box 13)
  - Bardoux, J., excerpts from his article in Capital
  - Barsoff, General A. F., report on aviation presented to Czar in autumn, 1916
  - Battle action in Eastern Prussia, 1914
  - Battle notes of the staff of the Russian 29th Infantry Division during the 1914 campaign
  - Borisov, V. E., letter, 1931 July
  - British Government, on support given to the Russian White Armies (March-June 1919)
  - Buchinskii, Iu. F., notes on the battles in East Prussia
  - Bukhovskii, A. D., documents on the battle at Sukhodol
  - Burlin, P. and Stavitsky, P. P., letters regarding Sino-Japanese War in 1938
  - Cavalry attacks on the Russian Front
  - Cheriachukin, General A., "Action of the 7th Cavalry Division in the War with Germany during the First Days of the General Mobilization Declaration in 1914"
  - Chernavin, V., "28th Artillery Brigade in the Vicinity of Gumbinen, August 6-7 (19-20), 1914"
  - Dobrogorsky, N., "Siberian Riflemen in East Prussia"
  - Dragomirov, General A. M., excerpts from his "Brief Outline of Military Action of the Composite/Subsequently 16th/Cavalry Division in 1914"
  - Dukhonin, General N., as described by his widow in 1937
  - Egorov, Major General A. E., "Notes on Action of the IX Army Corps and 42nd Infantry Division during the Inception of Struggle for Galicia in 1914"
  - Evstaf'ev, V., letter on action of the 110th Infantry Kama Regiment in the vicinity of Gumbinen
  - Fock, General, description of the defenders of Port Arthur during the Russo-Japanese War of 1905-1906
  - Galka, Lt. L. K., notes on the 58th Prague Regiment of 15th Division
  - German Headquarters on the Don, correspondence, 1918
  - Gol'mblad, F. Fr., "To What Is Rennenkampf's Fault Attributable?"
  - Gosudarstvennaia Duma i Gosudarstvennoi Sovet (Report to Czar on measures for state defense and reply from General V. Gourko)
  - Iakovlev, Colonel, "Description of the Battle Waged by the 34th Infantry Division, October 8, 1915"
  - Income tax returns, 1925-1943
  - Klepikov, F., letter to B. V. Savinkov, 1921 September 27 (Box 14)
  - Krasnov, General P., "New Historical Work of Professor General N. N. Golovin"
  - "The Labinskii Division in February 1920"
  - Lashkevitch, A. F., diary, 1915 March - 1916 May
  - Leaflet commemorating the 81st Cavalry of Catherine the Great and Prince Georgii M. Apsheronskii, Nos. 2 and 3
  - Lukomsky, Lt. General, "Action of the 32nd Infantry Division, May 1 -September 15, 1916"
  - Lukomsky, Lt. General, telegram to A. I. Guchkov on beginning of "democratization" of the army in 1917
  - Maklakoff, V. A., paper on Russia, 1940 March 12
  - Maps
  - Melgunov, S. P., "Russian Counter-Revolution," lecture delivered at the Academic Association in Paris, 1938 June 17
  - Mileant, General G., "Reminiscences on Stay with I Army in 1914"
  - Minchin, General, memoirs on military action of the 2nd Army from August 10-18, 1914
  - Molchanov, General, "Izhev Workers in Their Struggle with the Bolsheviks" (Box 15)
  - Nebo, Colonel M., "General P. K. Rennenkampf as Educator of the Commanding Personnel"
  - "Nicholas," a biography of the Grand Duke Nikolai Nikolaevitch
  - Pacific and Far East, documents and papers
  - Personal accounts of various participants on the Russian front
  - Polunin, A., "Comments on General Golovin's Report Concerning Cavalry Organization"
  - Postovsky, General P., letters relating to catastrophe of General Samsonoff's army in August 1914
  - Preobrazhensky, Captain, notes on battle action of Russian troops in 1915 near Kieltsky, Kobrin, Piaski, and Travniki
  - Puchkov, F. A., "8th Kam Rifle Division in the Siberian Ice March, 1931" parts I and II
  - Puchkov, F. A., notes on assignment to Ufa
  - von Ridel, Lieutenant Fieldmarshal, memorandum on the battles fought by the Russian Cavalry against units of the Austro-German Army in Galicia, 1915 September
  - Road capacity information
  - Russian Academic Association in Paris, minutes, 1939 June 5
  - Russian Army, report on future organization
  - Russian Army during the war, reports
  - Russian emigre military-scientific activities, letters and documents
  - Russian Military Union, circulars (Box 16)
  - Shkinsky, General Ia. F., memoirs
  - Shol'p, Major General, "First Landing at Kirilovka, April 1921"
  - Shol'p, Major General "Notes on the Great War, 1915-1916-1917"
  - Society of Russian Officers of General Staff Headquarters, Central Committee, announcement
  - "Spisok chastei Rossiiskoi Armii vystypivshikh na voinu v godu, ili sformirovannykh vo vremia voiny" (list of divisions of the Russian Army in 1914)
  - Stremaukhov, N., letter on action of XVII Army Corps
  - Tatarinov, A., "At the Foot of the Carpathian Mountains in 1915"
  - Tatarinov, A., "Autumn Operations in the Vicinity of Rovno, 1915"
  - Timchenko-Iareshchenko, Colonel, "The Great War, 1915-1916"
  - Timchenko-Iareshchenko, Colonel, "The 204th Ardagen-Mikhail Infantry Regiment, 51st Infantry Division, 1917"
  - Verderevsky, M. A., report on the past and future organization of the Russian infantry
  - Voennoe Delo Zagranitsei, Belgrade, 1924 October
  - von Waldsteten, Egon "The Battle by Turinka, August 24, 1914," Nashata Konnitsa, 1927 February-March
  - Wrangel, General P., letter to General A. I. Denikin, 1920 February 15
- CLIPPINGS, 1922-1939 (Box 16)
  Clippings arranged alphabetically by title and subject.
  - "Contemporary Strategical-Political Situation in China," Russkii Invalid, 1922 November, December (Box 16)
  - "Foch," Novoe Vremia, 1929 March 23
  - "General Golovin's Work 'Russian Counter-Revolution in 1917-1918' and Klauzevits' Teaching," Russkii Invalid, 1939 June 20
  - "Letters on Military Self-Education"
  - Pacific and Far East
  - "The Problem of Tsaritsyn," Signal, 1939 June 15
  - "Strategical Attack of State Historian S. P. Melgunov," Signal, 1939 July 1
- MISCELLANY, 1927-1943 (Boxes 17-18)
  - Articles in the Russian emigre press on Russia and the Soviet Union, lists of (Box 17)
    - Dni, 1927-1928
    - Golos Rodiny, 1936-1938
    - Nasha Gazeta, 1938-1939
    - Posledniia Novosti, 1928-1929, 1936-1939
    - Rul', 1927-1929
    - Segodnia, 1927-1929
    - Vozrozhdenie, 1927-1929
    - Various publications, 1932-1933
  - Correspondence
    - General
    - Poliakov, V., 1943
  - Institut Izucheniia Sovremennykh Problem Voiny i Mira (Institute for the Study of Contemporary Problems of War and Peace) (Box 18)
  - "Kratkii Otchet o Deiatel'nosti Voennago Ministerstva za god" (Brief Account of the Activities of the War Ministry for 1916)
    From the personal archives of Grand Duke Nikolai Nikolaevich.
  - Lists of materials received by Hoover Library, 1931-1933
  - Obshchestvo Druzei Natsional'noi Rossii v Zagrebe (Society of Friends of National Russian in Zagreb), 1939
  - Pis'ma Gen. Lukomskago k Gen. Golovinu o bol'shoi voennoi programe g. 1917 (Letters to General Golovin from General Lukomskii on the big military program of 1917), 1934
  - Russkaia Osvoboditel'naia Armiia (Russian Liberation Army)
  - Russkii Komitet po Ustroistvu Uchebnykh Zavedenii (Russian Committee for the Organization of Institutions of Learning), Paris
  - Writings
    - "Puti Vozrozhdeniia Rossii" (The Paths to Russia's Re-Birth), 1941 July 29
    - "Russkii Natsionalizm" (Russian Nationalism), undated